<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Przemek Zientala</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2021-08-12T22:10:00-04:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Przemek Zientala</name>
   <email>p.zientala.1995@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Print a stranger's identity at your local post office</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/12/ups-store-print-privacy/"/>
   <updated>2021-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/08/12/ups-store-print-privacy</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-extraordinary-visit&quot;&gt;An (extra)ordinary visit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here’s a little story for today. The other day I needed to print some documents at a local UPS store. After arriving, I quickly found out that the only options are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the PCs to download the docs and send the printing job to the printers there
OR&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Send an email to a store employee who would print them out for me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the privacy and security-conscious ones among us, this should already raise huge red flags:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What if you log in to your email inbox and forget to log off, realizing only a couple hours or days later?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What if there is a physical keylogger capturing your login details?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What if someone pointed the OS to make DNS reuqests to a malicious DNS server, routing you to malicious websites despite you typing in the right URL?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do you really ensure that the employee deleted the email you sent them containing your sensitive documents?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few things that come to mind, and all of them are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; real possibilities [TODO: add real-world examples to each point if possible]. It’s extremely unlikely that I’m the only one who has ever thoughts of this, and given the number of varous post office stores offering printing services in the US alone, and the number of bad actors out there, I would be very surprised if at least some of those things are not happening as I’m typing this. “Oh, come on, Windows 10 has a firewall that’s on by default” you might say. At least in that UPS store it was &lt;em&gt;disabled&lt;/em&gt;, which is of course a can of worms from a security standpoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever thought “I want to start my life all over again”? Well, your local post office with printing service might got you covered. If you’re into identity theft, simply go to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Downloads&lt;/code&gt; folder on the PC and copy all the files there onto your pendrive (be a good person and &lt;strong&gt;don’t do that&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-see-who-you-really-are&quot;&gt;Let’s see who you really are&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was absolutely terrified at just how sensitive information was left in that folder, and by the sheer number of documents. Even without opening any of the files, I saw insurance policy details, student IDs, driver’s license and passport photocopies, and many more. Put some of these things together and you’re giving the bad guys more than they need to steal your identity and literally turn your life upside down. Your perfect credit score that you worked so hard for over the years? Yeah, that’s gone, and with it so many things that follow. Access to your bank account and your money? You’ll certainly find out once your internet stops working and your landlord comes knocking at your door for that overdue rent payment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-i-really-need-to-print-now&quot;&gt;But I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need to print &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, you should always treat machines that you don’t trust as compromised. This leads to the simplest “fix” for this security nightmare - just don’t use printing services at post office locations, period. Get your own computer and printer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above is easier said than done, though. Perhaps you’ve just moved to a new apartment and you don’t have your printer there yet. What are the next best things you can do, if you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; can’t wait? Here are some ways to minimize the risks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ask-your-neighbours-to-print-your-stuff-for-you-make-sure-you-trust-them&quot;&gt;Ask your neighbours to print your stuff for you (make sure you trust them!)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Side benefit: you’ll get to know them better, and &lt;a href=&quot;TODO: link needed&quot;&gt;research hsa shown&lt;/a&gt; that doing favours for someone makes them like you more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bring-your-own-stuff&quot;&gt;Bring your own stuff&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring your own laptop to the post office, add the printer, and send the printing job to the printer
This might not always be possible, in case you can’t (or don’t want to) connect to the post office’s local network&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re less extreme, bring your own keyboard if you’re worried about physical keyloggers (still - check the USB ports for any suspicious dongles). People might look at you in a weird way if you really bring your own keyboard. However, if you really want to avoid physical keyloggers, that’s the safest option&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-download&quot;&gt;Don’t download&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of downloading the file, many browsers allow you to open the file without persisting it to disk. This is what you should generally use, since even after downloading the file and removing it from &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Trash&lt;/code&gt;, it can still technically be recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-factor-authentication&quot;&gt;2-factor authentication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure that whichever accounts you log in on the post office PC have 2FA enabled, and that you change passwords for all of them after you come back home
Remeber, we’re assuming that these machines have been compromised. Changing a couple of passwords is easy these days, especially if you’re using a password manager. There’s really no excuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above are all short-term fixes, however. What can be done in the long term?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;back-to-the-basics&quot;&gt;Back to the basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people don’t follow the latest developments in software security, nor should they have to in order to ensure their data is safe. So, what can be done to prevent &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Downloads&lt;/code&gt; folders being full of highly sensitive informaiton just waiting to be exploited?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;account-logoff-process-changes&quot;&gt;Account logoff process changes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple fix is to implement software security measures such as wiping the contents of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Downloads&lt;/code&gt; or, even better, the entire account, after logging off. I would imagine this is a standard feature of guest accounts on Windows 10 (TODO: check), so I’m surprised this was turned off at the UPS store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-factor-authentication-enforcement&quot;&gt;2-factor authentication enforcement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is obvious - if you &lt;em&gt;have to&lt;/em&gt; use these PCs, at the very least have 2FA enabled for the accounts you log in on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;raising-awareness&quot;&gt;Raising awareness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The files left in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Downloads&lt;/code&gt; folder are a direct consequence of people not removing them from there. Therefore, educating people on basic security and privacy topics should continue and even increase in intensity, as the massive move to the digital space goes on around the world. Although this option is slow and costly, remember this: prevention is always better than treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>To sleep or not to sleep? That is (not) the question</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/04/sleep-fitbit/"/>
   <updated>2021-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/08/04/sleep-fitbit</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;fitbit-more-like-sleepbit&quot;&gt;Fitbit? More like Sleepbit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My amazing girlfriend once had a great idea for a Christmas gift - a small Fitbit. She also got one, which helped us stay fit by encouraging each other to beat each other’s stats. A great side effect I discovered only later on is that wearing the Fitbit every day for 1.5 years generated tons of detailed sleep tracking data. And I really mean &lt;em&gt;tons&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next thing was to get all that data. Knowing how companies tend to make their products as limited as possible in terms of access to your own data, I didn’t have much hope. However, it turns out that Fitbit allows you to export all of your data in… JSON and CSV formats! What a news was that to me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exploration-time&quot;&gt;Exploration time!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To uncover what my sleep data tries to tell me, I did an in-depth analysis of 1.5 years’ worth of data. &lt;a href=&quot;https://mybinder.org/v2/gh/slazien/fitbit_analysis/4140b6c56bfb1b448364fc58344d23383c86e387?filepath=notebooks%2Fmain_analysis.ipynb&quot;&gt;An interactive Jupyter notebook is available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;main-conclusions&quot;&gt;Main conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seems to confirm that going to sleep on time improves sleep quality.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Confirms my feeling of “not being a dreamer” - I regularly get less REM sleep than I should for my age. This will have to be further diagnosed by a sleep doctor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Confirms that I’m a “light sleeper” quite literally - the vast majority of my sleep stages are light sleep, sometimes to the point of being disproportionately frequent. This partially explains my occasional tiredness during the day.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shows that the duration of a single deep sleep episode as well as the total deep sleep time per night is highly variable, which helps explain days where I feel very refreshed one day and tired the next one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, this was a great exercise in data wrangling and using using Plotly to make interactive graphs. I hope you enjoy it as much as I did!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>On speed limits and lane counts on highways</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/16/highways/"/>
   <updated>2021-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/16/highways</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently moved out of Paris due to soon ending my wonderful journey with Datadog. Thanks to my parents helping me out, it was much easier than doing it all alone. Still, this was a much more logistically complicated process than I initially thought:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I couldn’t travel by airplane, as the amount of luggage to transport would cost me an arm and a leg. I didn’t want to leave my luggage to be transported by a moving company, as I had a few very important personal items.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;COVID is still a thing, meaning - tests. Coordinating taking a test within 72h of arrival to France (travelling through Germany) required a bit of planning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, while driving / riding a car for &amp;gt; 1700 km one-way (Warsaw &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Paris), you have lots of time to think. &lt;em&gt;And think I did&lt;/em&gt;. “What about”, you ask? Naturally, about highways, which constituted probably &amp;gt; 75% of the total distance travelled by us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of my observations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Significant parts of German highways (“autobahns”) have &lt;em&gt;no speed limits&lt;/em&gt;, no strings attached. No such thing in Poland and France.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where speed limits exist, there are noticeable differences between countries (Poland having the highest limit of 140 km/h, France and Germany both having 130 km / h)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The distribution of speed limit areas changes between countries (it seems there are more in Germany than in Poland)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Polish drivers seem to obey speed limits more rarely than German and French drivers (purely based on my observations - perhaps this is because Poles are rarely fined due to many fewer speed cameras, and the fines being lower?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given all the above, you’d think that getting from point A to B in Poland would be the fastest of the three countries. Turns out, you would be &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;. After nearly 30 h spent on highways in all these countries, here are my observations and hypotheses that explain this apparent paradox:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;German and French highways primarily have 3 lanes, while Polish ones have 2. This is a surprisingly big deal, &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more important than any speed limits. Why? Highways are the primary “arteries” through which heavy trucks transport goods. These trucks are slow compared to passenger cars, and so they stick to driving on the rightmost lane. Here’s what happens depending on the number of langes:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;On a 3-lane highway, this leaves the middle lane for medium-speed passenger cars, and leftmost lane for high-speed cars and overtakers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;On a 2-lane highway, the only lane left for passenger cars (both medium and high-speed) is the leftmost one.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what happens if a truck decides to overtake another truck, or if a particularly slow passenger car stays on the left lane? On a 3-lane we’re fine. This still leaves the leftmost lane free. On a two-way, we have a problem. All the cars on that lane will be speed-limited by the slowest-moving car, with no way of overtaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phenomenon was extremely obvious when 3-lane highways in Germany temporarily narrowed to 2 lanes - the whole traffic slowed down by ~ 20 - 30 km / h on average, regardless of the speed limit. This seems to me like the biggest factor behind why driving on Polish highways will be &lt;em&gt;slower&lt;/em&gt; than on German ones, despite a higher speed limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While German speed limits seem more frequent than Polish ones, they are introduced gradually, while the Polish ones - more abruptly. E.g. if there is a sharp turn, the speed on a German highway will be gradually reduced to 120 -&amp;gt; 100 -&amp;gt; 80 or similar. In Poland, there is typically only one speed limit reduction, right down to the lowest speed. This makes “fast traffic jams” on the Polish highways, which contributes to slowing down the overall traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;German highways are famously smooth. This means that no speed reductions are needed before surface irregularities such as holes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s clear there was a lot of clever planning done when designing these highways in Germany, and this really contributes to making it a pleasure to drive on them.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A quantitative look at happiness</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/30/happiness/"/>
   <updated>2021-05-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/30/happiness</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-questions-than-answers&quot;&gt;More questions than answers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not too long ago, I took a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/the-science-of-well-being&quot;&gt;happiness course&lt;/a&gt; on coursera - “The science of well-being” by Laurie Santos. It is a fantastic, eye-opening course about what &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; makes us happy, as opposed to what our brains make us &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; makes us happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After taking the course, lots of questions naturally came to mind: are all people happy on more or less the same level around the world? Does money &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; not make us happy? Can we predict collective happiness levels of societies by looking at suicide rates? All questions, no answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-to-the-rescue&quot;&gt;Data to the rescue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, to have a go at answering these, I had to find relevant data. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/mathurinache/world-happiness-report&quot;&gt;World Happiness Report data&lt;/a&gt; looked great for my purpose. I also found a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/russellyates88/suicide-rates-overview-1985-to-2016&quot;&gt;suicide rates overview dataset&lt;/a&gt; which I later merged with the happiness one. Data cleaning clearly took the longest due to some inconsistencies and missing data in several datasets. However, afterwards, it was mostly smooth sailing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/slazien/happiness_analysis/blob/master/happiness.ipynb&quot;&gt;The complete analysis of both datasets is here - have a look if you want to dive deeper into the methods used and see the graphs.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, the data mostly supported what I learned in the course, and gave me some answers to my questions. The most important conclusions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Money is not as important as we think in making us happy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Good relationships and good health are important contributors to our happiness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. The degree to which you’re happy / likely to commit a suicide varies considerably with where you live in the world&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. High / low suicide rates don’t imply low / high happiness scores. In other words - suicide rates are poor predictors of happiness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now go talk to your family and friends, have a walk in the nature or have a run - this is almost sure to make you more happy :)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Another attempt at a personal blog</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/29/introduction/"/>
   <updated>2021-05-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/29/introduction</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is my &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; attempt at consistently keeping a personal blog up-to-date. Trying this out several years ago I failed, which taught me several lessons that will, hopefully, make things better this time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keeping it simple.&lt;/strong&gt; My old personal website was too complicated to update. Say hi to procrastination.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Staying focused.&lt;/strong&gt; What is my goal with a personal blog? I didn’t use to have a clear goal, which means I didn’t have an incentive to keep it up to date.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keeping records of my learning helps with motivation.&lt;/strong&gt; This is tied to the previous point. I want to have some sort of a virtual “diary” where I note down what I learned. &lt;em&gt;“Use a personal notepad like Joplin”&lt;/em&gt;, I hear you say. The issue is - my notes tend to become messy, and by expecting &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; visitors, it makes me think twice (* 10) before publishing. &lt;em&gt;Does it have any value to the reader?&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Is it easily comprehensible?&lt;/em&gt; are just a couple of questions that I hope will improve my writing skills. As an aspiring Data Scientist, being a good writer is arguably a crucial skill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And… that’s about it! I have kept it short this time to make sure that I can get started with &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;, however small (thanks &lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
