<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Przemek Zientala</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2021-05-29T18:27:23+02:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Przemek Zientala</name>
   <email>p.zientala.1995@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Another attempt at a personal blog</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/29/introduction/"/>
   <updated>2021-05-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/29/introduction</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is my &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; attempt at consistently keeping a personal blog up-to-date. Trying this out several years ago I failed, which taught me several lessons that will, hopefully, make things better this time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keeping it simple.&lt;/strong&gt; My old personal website was too complicated to update. Say hi to procrastination.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus.&lt;/strong&gt; What is my goal with a personal blog? I didn’t use to have a clear goal, which means I didn’t have an incentive to keep it up to date.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keeping records of my learning.&lt;/strong&gt; This is tied to the previous point. I want to have some sort of a virtual “diary” where I note down what I learned. &lt;em&gt;“Use a personal notepad like Joplin”&lt;/em&gt;, I hear you say. The issue is - my notes tend to become messy, and by expecting &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; visitors, it makes me think twice (* 10) before publishing. &lt;em&gt;Does it have any value to the reader?&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Is it easily comprehensible?&lt;/em&gt; are just a couple of questions that I hope will improve my writing skills. As an aspiring Data Scientist, being a good writer is arguably a crucial skill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And… that’s about it! I have kept it short this time to make sure that I can get started with &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;, however small (thanks &lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
